"Is It Safe to
Eat Raw Mushrooms?"
There is a toxin in plain
white button mushrooms
called agaritine, which
may be carcinogenic.
And plain white button mushrooms
grow up to be cremini mushrooms
(the brown mushrooms), and cremini
mushrooms grow up to be
portobello mushrooms—they’re
all the exact same mushroom.
It’s like how green bell peppers
are just unripe red bell peppers.
But you can reduce the amount
of agaritine in these shrooms
through cooking.
Frying, microwaving, boiling,
or even just freezing and
thawing lowers the levels.
It is therefore recommended to
cook mushrooms before consumption,
something I noted in a video
that’s now more than a decade old.
But if you look at the
various cooking methods
the agaritine isn’t
completely destroyed.
Take dry baking for example:
10 minutes at about
400 degrees Fahrenheit
(basically how you’d make a pizza),
only cuts the agaritine levels
by about a quarter, so
77 percent still remains.
Boiling looks better,
appearing to wipe out over half
of the toxin after just five minutes.
But it’s not actually wiped
out; instead, it’s just
transferred to the cooking water.
So yes, levels within
the mushrooms drop
by about half at five minutes
and 90 percent after an hour,
but that’s mostly because
it’s leaching into the broth.
So, if you’re making soup or something,
five minutes of boiling is
no better than the pizza,
and even after an
hour about half remains.
Frying for 5 to 10 minutes
wipes out a lot,
but microwaving is a more
healthful way to cook,
and it works even better.
Just one minute in the microwave
“reduce[s] the agaritine content
of the [fresh sliced] mushrooms
by 65 percent,” and only
30 seconds wipes out about half.
So, microwaving is
probably the easiest way
to reduce agaritine levels
in fresh mushrooms.
What I do with dried mushrooms
is throw them into pasta water
when I’m making spaghetti and
between the 20-ish percent drop
from the drying and the 60
percent-ish drop from boiling
for 10 minutes and straining,
more than 90 percent is wiped out.
Should we be concerned
about the residual agaritine?
Should we skip mushroom pizza?
If you’re eating pizza, mushrooms
are probably the last thing
you need to worry about, but seriously
should we be concerned
about agaritine?
According to a review paid
for by the mushroom industry,
not at all. “The available
evidence to date suggests
that agaritine from consumption
of . . . mushrooms poses
no known toxicological
risk to healthy humans.”
The researchers acknowledge
it’s considered a potential
carcinogen in mice, but
then you have to extrapolate
that data to human health outcomes.
For example, the Swiss Institute
of Technology estimated
the average mushroom consumption
in the country would be
expected to cause about two
cases of cancer per 100,000 people.
That’s actually similar
to U.S. consumption,
so one could theoretically
expect about 20 cancer deaths
per million lives from
mushroom consumption.
Now typically with a
new chemical, pesticide,
or food additive we’d
like to see less than
one in a million cancer risk.
By this approach, “the average
mushroom consumption …
would be 20-fold too
high to be acceptable.”
To get it down to one in a
million you could only eat
about a half cup serving
once every 250 days
or something to remain
under the “tolerable” limit.
But to put that into perspective,
even if you were eating
a single serving every
single day, the resulting
additional cancer risk would
only be about 1 in 10,000.
In other words, “if 10,000
people consumed a mushroom meal
daily for 70 year[s],
then in addition to the
3,000 cancer cases
arising from other factors,
one more case could be
attributed to consuming mushrooms.”
But again, this is all
based on the presumption that
results in mouse models
are valid in humans;
this is all just
extrapolating from mice.
What we need is a huge
prospective study to examine
the association between mushroom
consumption and cancer risk
in people, but there weren’t
any such studies until... now.
“Mushroom consumption and
risk of … cancer in [the]
two large [Harvard] cohorts”, and…
"no association between
mushroom [intake] and [cancer]”.
Eating raw or undercooked
shiitake mushrooms can cause
something else, though: shiitake
mushroom ﬂagellate dermatitis.
Flagellate as in flagellation,
whipping, flogging.
Check out this crazy rash.
You break out in a rash
that makes it look as if
you’ve been whipped.
Doesn’t it look wild?
That’s just how you break out.
It’s thought to be caused by
a compound in shiitake mushrooms
called lentinan, but
because heat denatures it,
it only seems to be a problem
with raw or undercooked mushrooms.
Now it’s rare; only about 1 in
50 people are even susceptible.
And it goes away on its
own in a week or two.
Interestingly, it can strike
as many as 10 days after you
eat them, which is why people
may not make the connection.
One poor guy suffered on and off
for 16 years before a diagnosis.
Hopefully a lot of doctors
will watch this video,
and if they ever see a rash like this,
they’ll tell their patients
to cook their shiitakes.